Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
Burnt Field (Part 1)
（島田(しまだ)）アッ… アア…
（零(れい)）え〜っと その…
Um...
Uh...
（二海堂(にかいどう)）ンッ… ンンッ…
（零）これは 何というか…
I mean, what in the...
SHOGI MAESTRO
TOURNAMENT
The Babbling Stream Inn
Seiryuuen
Ladies' plan includes
spa services
and lunch course
Ladies' plan includes
spa services
and lunch course
Ladies' plan includes
spa services
and lunch course
The pair of eastern
shogi princes present
Demonstration board commentary
Various receptions planned
前回にも増して
ひどいというか何というか…
It's even worse than the previous one.
I mean...
The pair of eastern
shogi princes present
Demonstration board commentary
Why do we have a close-up?
なんで俺たちがアップなの？
"The pair of eastern shogi princes"?
“東の将棋王子ペア”？
この楕円の枠が
いけないんですかね？
I don't know about those oval frames around you two.
何ていうか こう—
It's like photos of students who were
absent on the day of the yearbook photo.
卒業アルバムの欠席の人みたいで…
Well, they kept taking photo after photo.
いや…　取ったら取ったで—
今度は 何つうか “天国から
いつも見守ってるよ”的な—
But then it had this "We're always watching you from Heaven" vibe.
空気感が出ちゃってさ…
（零）もうやってみたんスね…
So you tried it, then.
It's difficult raising funds for
the Shogi Maestro Tournament.
（島田）
棋匠(きしょう)戦は 資金繰りが難しくてさ
I asked Nakamura, the general manager of the Shogi Association, to come up with a design.
将棋連盟の総務の中村(なかむら)君に
デザイン頼んだんだけど
タダなんだけど
やっぱ厳しいよな…
but without spending any money, it's a tall order.
Yeah, I thought it'd be easy.
（中村）
いやぁ 簡単と思ったんスけどねえ
Designing is tough after all.
やっぱデザインって難しいッスねえ
That's strange.
おっかしいなぁ
I was in the Computer Club when I was in college.
大学では
パソコン部だったんスけどねえ
（島田）あまりの盛り下がりすぎに
ついに会長もキレちゃってさ…
His initial enthusiasm had been so
dampened that the chairman lost it.
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)）うん もういい！
いいよ！　うん！
Yes!
That's enough!
It's fine!
Yes!
In fact, why don't we showcase their feebleness?
Strict
budget
New
ideas
もういっそ
病弱を前面に出してこうよ！
We can have a stationary camera
もう据え置きカメラでさ
Live stream
Time remaining
Heart rate
that displays their EKG and heart rate along with the time remaining in the match!
残り時間と一緒に—
心電図と心拍数
出しとこうよ！
And we can have a nurse standing by in the next room!
（神宮寺）隣の部屋にもさ
看護師さんとか待機させてさ
もう いつ どちらが倒れても
大丈夫！　…みたいにさ
Like, "If either one of them collapses, there's nothing to worry about!"
Toku! Enough already!
（柳原）徳(とく)ちゃん！
いいかげんにしてよ！
Proposals
That kind of mockery is too cruel!
あんまりだよ そんな茶化(ちゃか)し方
Proposals
Gap
This might be a relatively small-scale event,
but it's one of seven prestigious major titles!
Gap
（柳原）
ちょっとばかし規模は小さいけど
Gap
由緒ある７大タイトルの
ひとつなんだぜ
Gap
The Shogi Maestro Tournament is my life!
棋匠戦は 俺の命なんだ！
Proposals
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
We have support from five papers, but they're all small local newspapers, so the budget was cut.
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
５紙協賛っつっても みんな
小さい地方紙で予算を削られて—
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Announcements
New ideas
Sponsors
Strict budget
Gap
We need to tighten our belts right now!
Surely you understand that!
Gap
今 厳しいんだってば！
分かるだろう！
Gap
Even at the best of times, it overlaps with
the Master Tournament, so business is slow!
69th
Master Tournament
Challenger
Kumakura Kengo, 9-dan
Master Souya Touji
Surpass the legend
ただでさえ
名人戦と ほぼ同時開催で—
閑古鳥が鳴いてるっていうのに！
If we lose even more spectators and attention,
これ以上
動員も注目も下がりまくったら—
starting next year, the Shogi Maestro Tournament...
来年から棋匠戦は…
Glare
will have all of its matches right here!
全局 ここでやるからな！
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
A 5-minute
walk
from Tokyo JR
Sendagaya Station
ギャ〜ッ！
So I appreciate your help.
（島田）…というわけで—
よろしくね
Whether or not next year's Shogi Maestro Tournament
will be held entirely at the shogi hall depends on you guys.
来年の棋匠戦が オール将棋会館に
なっちゃうかどうかは—
君たちにも懸かってるから
So don't hold anything back.
もう遠慮なく—
ドッカンドッカン
盛り上げちゃってちょうだいね
Give a lively commentary.
Hahaha
Haha
Haha...
Hahaha
Haha
Haha...
*These two are providing the demo board commentary.
Gulp
Heavy responsibility
Various receptions
いや…
でも 来てくれて助かったよ
But it really helped that you came.
Truly.
（島田）ホント
（零）えっ？
Huh?
Of course I'll do my best with the demo board commentary!
もちろん頑張りますよ 大盤解説
あっ…　なぜですか？
兄者　そんな急に改まって
But what's with all the gratitude, Big Brother?
（島田）今に分かるよ
You'll find out soon.
Hey!
（柳原）よう！
Kan! Long time no see!
カンちゃん　久しぶり！
How've you been?
元気にしてた？
Kaku! Yasu! It's been a long time!
角(かく)ちゃん 康(やす)ちゃん　久しぶり
How are you doing?
どうよ？　調子は
Hey, Saku!
（角ちゃん）よう 朔(さく)ちゃん
Shogi Maestro Yanagihara! Long time no see.
（康ちゃん）
柳原棋匠　お久しぶりです
Filled
to
the
Filled
to
the
Filled
to
the
brim
Filled
to
the
brim
Filled
to
the
brim
Filled
to
the
brim
Filled
to
the
brim
Filled
to
the
brim
Well, here's our third pre-toast!
（関係者）
そんじゃ まあ ３度目のプレ乾杯！
Ready?!
（関係者）いよ〜っ！
Cheers!
（一同）乾杯！
Bam
（柳原）うえ〜い！　ハハハハッ！
今年も会えてうれしいよ
I'm thrilled to see all of you again this year.
Rowdy
Thank you, everyone!
（柳原）ありがとう みんな！
（関係者）よっ！　朔ちゃん！
Rowdy
Hey, Saku!
Wh-What is this?
（零）こ… これは…
これが曲者(くせもの)なんだよ
A devious person.
棋匠戦の…
There's this formidable home game feeling at the Shogi Maestro Tournament.
この恐るべきホーム感
来てる記者 関係者が
ほとんど柳原さんの身内感覚
Most of the reporters and staffers here are like Yanagihara's pals.
The Shogi Maestro Tournament challenger
is stuck with this awful away game feeling.
（島田）棋匠戦の挑戦者は—
まず このすげえアウエー感と
戦うハメになるんだよ
Hug
I missed you, Saku!
（関係者）いやぁ 朔ちゃん
会いたかったよ！　ハハハハッ！
Hey, don't be such an old goat. I missed you too!
（柳原）
こら なんだよ このくそじじい
俺も会いたかったぜ！
Jeez, during this title match,
もうタイトル戦の間中—
風呂に行っても
サロンにコーヒー飲みに行っても
whether I take a bath, go to the lounge for coffee,
or have a meal, the atmosphere is always like this.
メシ食ってても 万事 こんな空気だ
もちろん往復の移動の間中もだ
Of course it's the same on the train going both ways.
どこへ行っても ご一行の声がする
No matter where I go, I hear a chorus of voices.
（島田）
あのじいさんの食えない所だよ
The old man is shrewd that way.
周りの空気から
自分のほうへ持ってっちまう
He makes himself the center of attention.
さすが66歳で現役Ａ級
He's 66-years-old and an active Class A player.
タイトル通算14期
バケモノのひとりだよ
He's won the title 14 times.
A true monster.
いや もう ここまで来たら
もののけのたぐいだ
Or after getting this far,
maybe more on the level of a vengeful ghost.
しかも 特大のな
An extra-large one.
But here in the fifth match, I have him on the ropes at 2-2.
だが この棋匠戦五番勝負
俺も ２−２まで追い詰めた
From the City of Shogi, Tendou, Let's Get a Master!
俺は欲しいよ
何に かじりついたとしても
I want it.
I'll bite into anything I can.
初タイトルが…
My first title!
絶対に取る　そして—
I swear I'll take it.
And with apologies to the old man,
あのじいさんの“同窓会”
申し訳ないが…
終わらせてやる
I'm going to end his reunions!
うん？
そういや がんちゃんは どうした？
By the way, where's Gan?
I don't see him.
がんちゃんがいねえな
R-Right.
He's here, but...
（関係者）
がんちゃん 来てはいるんだけど…
うん？　どうした？　具合でも？
What?
Is he ill?
（がんちゃん）さ… 朔ちゃん
S-Saku!
どうして？　前夜祭中だろうよ
What are you doing here? You got your match eve party.
（がんちゃん）
定年を繰り上げてくれって
内示をもらってな
I got an unofficial notice,
telling me to take early retirement.
５月いっぱいで
新聞社を退社したんだ
So I left the newspaper at the end of May.
まあ 早い話 リストラだ
Well, in a nutshell, I was laid off.
大事なタイトル戦の前日に
こんな景気の悪い話して—
I didn't want to cast a damper on the festivities the night before your important title match
with my story of economic woe.
勝負に水差したくなかったのに…
すまねえ 朔ちゃん
Sorry, Saku.
でも 朔ちゃん　俺は…
But when...
あんたは
まだ戦ってるんだって思ったら—
When I think about how you're still fighting,
居ても立ってもいられなくって…
I just can't sit still.
でっかいカメラ担いで
昼も夜もなく走り回ってさ
You were lugging around that huge camera day and night for years.
もう十分すぎるくらい
頑張ってきたんだ
You've done your best and then some.
がんちゃん　これからは人生
ゆっくり楽しんだらいいじゃねえか
Gan, shouldn't you relax and enjoy the rest of your life?
女房も そう言ってくれた　娘もな
That's what my wife said to me. So did my daughter.
でも…
But I'm scared.
怖(こえ)えなぁ
Without my work, what's left for me?
俺から仕事を取ったら
何が残ってんだ？
怖えよ 朔ちゃん
I'm scared, Saku.
（がんちゃん）まるで—
I feel like...
焼け野っ原にいるみてえだ
I'm in a burnt field.
I'm telling you, we should use this diagram!
（二海堂）だから
この図は使ったほうがいいって！
（零）いや
かえって分かりにくいって 二海堂
No, it's too confusing, Nikaidou!
Firm
It's better to put them up side-by-side and explain!
だから 実際に並べて
説明したほうがいいって！
Firm
Unyielding
We were told to keep it lively, remember?
盛り上げてくれって言われたろう！
Unyielding
Kiriyama, it'll go over better if we explain with pictures!
桐山(きりやま)　これは
絵で説明したほうがウケるって
23rd Children's Shogi Tournament
（棋士）懐かしいなぁ
This brings me back.
23rd Children's Shogi Tournament
俺も出たよ 子供獅子王戦
I participated in the Children's Lion King Tournament too.
（柳原）フッ…
それが今は指導する側だもんな
And now we coach it.
Hey, Saku. Where should I put up the shogi checkmate problems?
（棋士）なあ 朔ちゃん
詰め将棋問題って どこに貼る？
（柳原）ああ
子供が飽きてきたら 前に貼ろう
If the kids get bored, hang them up front.
（棋士）朔ちゃん　俺…
Saku, I'm...
降級が決まったんだ
being demoted.
（棋士）親父(おやじ)が倒れた
My old man collapsed.
田舎 帰るよ…
I'm moving back to the countryside.
（棋士）俺さ—
I'm going to retire and focus on coaching kids.
引退して
子供たちの指導に専念するよ
Saku, it's frustrating,
（棋士）朔ちゃん　悔しいけど…
俺 別の道探すよ…
but I'm going to look for another path.
（棋士）朔ちゃん　どうか…
Saku, please...
Keep fighting for us.
朔ちゃんは俺たちの分まで…
（泣き声）
ずっと… ずっと応援してるから
We'll always be cheering you on.
（柳原）どこへ行っても 自分が
いちばん年上になってから—
These days, wherever I go, I'm always the oldest one.
How long has it been like that?
一体 もう どれくらいたつだろう？
（男性Ａ）柳原さん すげえな
Yanagihara is amazing.
He's a monster.
（男性Ｂ）
バケモンだよ　もう66だぜ
The guy's 66-years-old.
And still Class A. How does he do it?
（男性Ｃ）
いまだＡ級って どういうことよ？
How long is he going to keep at it?
（男性Ｄ）
一体 いつまで ふんばる気だろう？
（柳原）一緒に戦ってきた仲間も
いつしか—
Somewhere along the line, the people who have been fighting alongside me have disappeared,
first one and then another.
１人消え ２人消え…
（柳原）あとに残ったものは…
All that's left now...
年老いた体と—
is this old body...
託された このおびただしい数の…
and these innumerable sashes...
タスキだけ
that have been entrusted to me.
重てえなぁ
They sure are heavy.
Burnt Field (Part 1)
Burnt Field (Part 2)
（記者）では 柳原棋匠は
現役最年長となるわけですが
Well, Shogi Maestro Yanagihara,
you're the eldest active Class A player.
How long do you think you'll be able to stay in Class A?
何歳まで
Ａ級に在籍できると思いますか？
If you were demoted, would you think about retiring?
降級したら引退を考えられますか？
（棋士Ａ）朔ちゃん　どうか…
Saku, please...
朔ちゃんだけは頑張ってくれ
Keep going for our sake!
I couldn't make my dream come true,
（棋士Ｂ）
俺が果たせなかった夢を—
but you can do it!
どうか 代わりに果たしてくれ…
（柳原）分かっている
I know.
分かっているよ
発する側には そんな—
The people who are departing...
don't feel like they're putting a curse on me.
呪(しゅ)をかけるような気持ちは
ないことを
怖えなぁ
I'm scared.
（がんちゃん）怖えよ 朔ちゃん
I'm scared, Saku.
まるで—
I feel like I'm standing in a burnt field.
焼け野っ原にいるみてえだ
（柳原）ただ託された—
But there are nights where...
幾百ものタスキに…
it feels like I'll get tangled in...
からめ捕られそうになる夜が
あるだけで…
the hundreds of sashes I've been entrusted with.
Blood pressure medicine, stomach medicine...
血圧の薬 胃薬
Cataract medicine, and... what else?
白内障の目薬と あとは…
てててっ…
どうせ 今 貼っても—
Ow...
Although I'm sure the effect won't last to the climax of the match.
佳境のころには
効かなくなってんだけどな　ハァ…
さて…
All right.
そろそろ行きますか
Guess I'd better get going.
Seiryuuen
So there's Shogi Maestro Yanagihara, the eldest Class A player with his seemingly-permanent title on the line,
（記者）さあ 永世が懸かった
最年長Ａ級 柳原棋匠と—
初タイトルが懸かった努力の人
島田八段
and Shimada, 8-dan,
a hardworking player going for his first title.
（記者）どっちが勝つか…
Who will win?
Whoever wins, it'll make for a bitter article.
（記者）どっちが勝っても
渋い記事になりますな　ハハハッ…
（記者）しっ…　静かに
Quiet.
Shimada, 8-dan, is here.
島田八段の入場だ
Good
luck
in
your
match
Kai
Good
luck
in
your
match
Kai
取りたい
I want to take it.
どうしても…
More than anything.
何があっても
No matter what.
（記録係）それでは
時間になりましたので—
And it is now time to begin.
Shogi Maestro Yanagihara, please make the first move.
先手 柳原棋匠で お願いします
Let's have a good match.
（柳原･島田）
よろしくお願いします
（記録係）先手 柳原棋匠　７六歩
Black, Shogi Maestro Yanagihara, P-7f.
White, Shimada, 8-dan, P-8d.
（記録係）後手 島田八段　８四歩
Huh?
（二海堂）えっ？
（零）３手目 １六歩？
P-1f is the third move?
An edge pawn?
何をたくらんでいる？
What's he up to?
だが…
But...
惑わされてたまるか
I won't let him throw me.
He's staying on the edge and advancing like that?
そのまま端を進めただと？
更に つき越して １五歩！
He's pushing on even more, with P-1e?!
オ〜ッ！　カッケー！
That's so cool!
Awesome! I've seen this before!
すげえ！　これ 俺 見たことある！
漫画で！
In a manga!
M-Manga?
ま… 漫画？　何の漫画？
What manga?
（島田）この妖怪め…
What a monster...
２手損してやるから
角を換えてこいだと？
Are you saying you'll give up two turns in exchange for my bishop?
You want to do a one-turn loss bishop exchange?
１手損角換わりでやろうってか？
だが 断る！
However, I refuse.
２手損だけは
ありがたく受け取ってやるが
I'll gratefully accept your two turns,
but I won't let you take control.
あんたに主導権は渡さんよ
B-2b+.
２二角成
（零）その戦いは—
A bishop exchange fourth file rook,
a difficult strategy in itself, as his fifth move
Shogi Maestro Tournament
Match Five
一筋を５手目につき越しての
角交換四間飛車(しけんびしゃ)という—
marked the beginning of this battle.
何とも言い難い戦型で始まった
Is Shogi Maestro Yanagihara inviting him to a bout of brute strength?
柳原棋匠は
腕力勝負を誘ってるんでしょうか？
“序盤なんて どうでもいい”
"The opening moves don't matter.
If I make this a hard fight, I'll have the upper hand."
Does it come from that confidence?
“力戦に持ち込めば 自分のほうが
上だ”という自信からですか？
No.
いや
島田さんの３五歩に—
In response to Shimada's P-3e,
he took almost no time exchanging the pawns at 8f with his rook,
ほぼノータイムで
８六歩と飛車を交換してきたので
so I think up to that point he's already studied these moves.
僕は
先まで研究済みの手だと思います
And plus...
そして—
初めてだ こんな形…
this is the first time I've seen this board state.
見たことないよ
I've never seen anything like it.
（零）粘り合いだった
They both persevered.
技術も 経験も
積み重ねてきた２人の…
They both had years and years of accumulated skill and experience.
島田さんは 柳原棋匠の研究に…
Shimada stubbornly persisted in resisting...
頑強に抵抗を続けた
Shogi Maestro Yanagihara's exploratory moves.
対局は終盤に さしかかり…
The match approached the endgame.
形勢のてんびんは…
The scales continued...
to tip back and forth, unrelentingly.
絶え間なく揺れ続けた
（零）そして 夕刻…
And then evening came.
He made a move.
（二海堂）指しました
G*5h.
５八金　５八金です
G*5h!
あっ…　あっ これは…
Oh, then Shimada, 8-dan...
島田八段…
（零）
この手で大きく優勢に傾きました！
With that move, he's gained a major advantage!
Shogi Maestro... Shogi Maestro Yanagihara...
（記者）棋匠　柳原棋匠
いつまで
Ａ級でいられると思いますか？
How long do you think you can remain in Class A?
Would you think about retiring if you were demoted from Class A?
Ａ級から落ちたら
引退を考えますか？
What do you think about the up-and-coming youngsters?
若手の台頭をどう思われますか？
（がんちゃん）怖えなぁ
I'm scared.
Without my work,
俺から仕事を取ったら—
何が残ってんだ？
what's left for me?
I'm scared, Saku.
怖えよ 朔ちゃん
（柳原）そうだな がんちゃん
I hear you, Gan.
俺も ずっと同じこと考えてる
I'm always thinking the same thing.
でも まだ答えは出てねえんだ
But I still don't have an answer.
ただ お前が立っているのが
焼け野原なのだとしたら…
However, if you're standing in a burnt field,
俺は まだ焼かれている真っ最中だ
then I'm still burning.
さて いこうか
Well, shall we go?
勝つことも そして—
Winning, and even losing,
負けることすら いつだって…
aren't things that can ever be decided so easily.
そうは簡単に
決まっちゃくれないもんなんだ
今日も また—
I'll become a human torch again today
火だるまになって—
存分に苦しんでやろうじゃないか
and give full rein to my suffering.
Burnt Field (Part 2)
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
Episode 40
（零）
柳原さんが見ているのは
この先の…
Yanagihara is looking beyond that.
He's good.
（島田）強い…
なにが現役最年長だ
Eldest active player, my ass!
He defended with the
bishop he just captured?
（二海堂）
今 取ったばかりの角で
受けた！
Was that the right move?
（島田）
良かったのか？
いや…
But...
If shogi is taken away from me,
what would be left?
（柳原）
俺から将棋を取ったら
何が残るんだろう？
Illustration: Itou Yuu
（零）今は
島田さんが攻めている
Shimada is on the offense right now.
柳原さんの
次の一手は…
What will Yanagihara's next move be?